Finding Aid for the Frank Lawrence Owsley Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Frank Lawrence Owsley Papers
1913-1959
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0003
12.6 linear_feet
The papers of Frank Lawrence Owsley which cover the period 1913 –1959 consist of ten cubic feet of materials and are primarily concerned with the professional life and career of this historian, author, and teacher. The major series in the papers include the Correspondence, the Writings, Personal and Biographical Materials, Agrarians, Publication Material, Academic Career, Professional Activities, and Research Materials.
Frank Lawrence Owsley Papers Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frank Lawrence Owsley which cover the period 1913 –1959 consist of ten cubic feet of materials and are primarily concerned with the professional life and career of this historian, author, and teacher. The major series in the papers include the Correspondence, the Writings, Personal and Biographical Materials, Agrarians, Publication Material, Academic Career, Professional Activities, and Research Materials.
In the Correspondence series the letters date from 1913 – 1956 (incoming) and 1927 –1956 (outgoing). 145 letters make up the Outgoing Correspondence sub series, and 2167 letters comprise the Incoming Correspondence. The letters cover a variety of topics: politics and issues of the period; academic concerns and correspondence with colleagues and former students; writings for various journals and other publications. There is correspondence with members of The Fugitive and Agrarian groups including Allen Tate, Robert Penn Warren, Donald Davidson, Andrew Lytle, and Herman Clarence Nixon. And there is substantial correspondence with his Colleagues Albert Burton Moore (93) from the University of Alabama and Oliver Perry Chitwood (94) with whom he wrote the two volume textbook A Short History of the Amercican People. Agrarian Herman Clarence Nixon also collaborated on this book.
The Writings series comes next with sub series of Book Manuscripts including Plain Folk of the Old South, King Cotton Diplomacy, and Selected Essays of Frank Lawrence Owsley. Unpublished Book Manuscripts; Articles, Essays, and Speeches; Unpublished Articles, Essays, and Speeches; And Book Reviews are other sub series. The series Personal and Biographical Material includes World War I documents, newspaper clippings, a 44 page photocopy of a memoir by Owsley, and other items. The Agrarian series consist of 3 folders: one on the 1936 Who Owns America?; a 1936 newspaper article on the South; and one on collecting papers of the Fugitives/Agrarians. The series Publication Material includes reviews of books by Owsley and a list of his articles. Professional Activities is a series which is comprised of the sub series Organizations and Events and includes minutes of the meetings of the Southern Historical Association and material of the Fugitive Reunion in 1956. Owsley’s Academic Career is the next series in the Papers and includes course syllabi, exams, lecture notes and class notes, his grade books from Vanderbilt University and the University of Alabama, and four student papers on the Civil War and Reconstruction. The final series in the papers and the most voluminous are the Research Materials and Notecards from his research for King Cotton Diplomacy. Blockade Running, Confederate Finances, Diplomacy, Mercenaries, Surveillance, Slavery Issues and many other subjects for his research for the book are included in these 20 boxes of Research Materials.
Frank Lawrence Owsley Chronology
1890 Born in Montgomery County, Alabama, January 20. Son of Lawrence Monroe and Annie Scott McGehee Owsley.
1892 – 1906 Attended several country schools in Montgomery and Elmore Counties. Some of the classes were taught by relatives.
1906 – 1909 Attended Fifth District Agricultural School, Wetumpka, Alabama. (The curriculum included two years of college.)
1909 Graduated from Fifth District Agricultural School in June, winning several medals and money prizes for highest honors.
1909-1911 Attended Alabama Polytechnic Institute, Auburn, Alabama, receiving bachelor of science degree in June 1911. He had a double major in English and History and was first in his class.
1912 Awarded the Master of Science in History with honors by Alabama Polytechnic Institute, Auburn, Alabama.
1912 –1914 Professor of History and Government at Fifth District Agricultural School, Wetumpka, Alabama.
1914 – 1915 Instructor in History at Alabama Polytechnic Institute, Auburn, Alabama.
1915-1916 Farmed and studied Law.
1916-1917 Attended graduate school at the University of Chicago, receiving the Master of Arts degree in History, June 1917.
1917-1919 Served briefly in Armed Services and returned to graduate school at the University of Chicago.
1919-1920 Professor of History, Birmingham-Southern College, Birmingham, Alabama.
1920 Married Harriet Fason Chappell in Birmingham, Alabama.
1920- 1924 Assistant Professor of History, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee
1924 Awarded Doctor of Philosophy degree, magna cum laude, by the University of Chicago.
1924 –1927 Associate Professor of History, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee.
1925 State Rights in the Confederacy published by University of Chicago Press.
1927-1928 Guggenheim Fellow in England and France for research on King Cotton Diplomacy.
1928 June 13, 1928 Frank Lawrence Owsley, Jr. (Larry) born in Nashville, Tennessee.
1928 –1949 Professor of History, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee
1930 I’ll Take My Stand: the South and the Agrarian Tradition published by Harper Brothers of New York and London. Owsley contributed the essay “The Irrepressible Conflict.”
1931 King Cotton Diplomacy, published by University of Chicago Press.
1936 Who Owns America? Published by Houghton, Miflin of New York and Boston. Owsley ontributed the essay “The Foundations of Democracy.”
1936 –1937 Social Science Research Grant and sabbatical leave from Vanderbilt University.
1937 Summer visiting professor, University of Illinois, Urbana, Illinois.
1938 March 12, 1938 Margaret Owsley (later Mrs. Cornelius Seigenthaler) born in Nashville, Tennessee.
1939 Summer visiting professor, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina
1940 Summer visiting professor, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina
1945 –1948 A Short History of the American People, volumes 1 and 2 by Frank Lawrence Owsley, Oliver Perry Chitwood and Herman Clarence Nixon published by D. Van Nostrand, Co. of New York.
1948 Walter Lynwood Fleming Lectures, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana. (These lectures were based on Plain Folk of the Old South.) 4 Lectures: April 12—“Southern Society—A Reinterpretation” and “To the Promised Land” April 13—“Southern Folkways” April 14: “The Role of the Plain Folk”
1948 The Claiborne Lectures at the University of Mississippi given in November. Tuesday November 2, “Role of the Plain Folk in Ante-Bellum Southern History” Wednesday November 3, “Southern Folkways”
1949 Plain Folk of the Old South published by Louisiana State University Press.
1949 – 1956 Friedman Professor of American History, University of Alabama.
1952 – 1955 Chairman, Department of History, University of Alabama.
1954 Summer visiting professor, Columbia University, New York City.
1955 Blazer Lectures, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky—“Self-Imposed Restraints and the Survival of American Democracy” (April 5, 1955)
1955 Summer visiting professor, Columbia University, New York City.
1956 Fulbright Lecturer, St. John’s College, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England.
1956 Died, October 21, in Winchester, England.
1969 The South: Old and New Frontiers: Selected Essays of Frank Lawrence Owsley. Edited by Harriet Chappell Owsley and published by University of Georgia Press.
1990 Frank Lawrence Owsley: Historian of the Old South: A Memoir by Harriet Chappell Owsley published in Nashville by the Vanderbilt University Press.
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing
    - 17 November 1916 – 16 March 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 19 November 1935 – 12 October 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 7 January 1941 – 20 May 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 26 May 1953 – 14 January 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 20 January 1954 – 3 November 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 8 February 1955 – 23 April 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 27 April 1956 – 30 October 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incoming
    - Abernethy, T. P. – Agar, Herbert (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Agar, Herbert – Alexander, Tom (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alexander, Tom (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Alexander, Tom (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Allen, John – Avant, W. L. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bagby, Muriel M. – Bailey, Thomas G. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bankhead, J. W. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Barnes, Barbara S. – Barnes, J. Ward (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Barnhart, John O. – Bethea, Barron (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Betterworth, John K. – Bird, Susan M. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Black, Hugo – Bragg, James W. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bramlett, F. – Branscomb, L. C. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Breedlove, J. P. – Bromley, E. W. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Brooks, Cleanth – Burgess, E. W. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Caldwell, Betty – Carey, L. J. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Carmichael, O. C. – Carter, Thomas H. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Caskey, William – Cayton, Horace (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chambers, D. L. – Cheney, Brainard (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - University of Chicago Press (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chitwood, O. P., 1940 –1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chitwood, O. P., 1943 –1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chitwood, O. P., 1947 - 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Chitwood, O. P., 1952 - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Church, W. – Clark, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cochran, P. – Coles, H. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Collins, Seward – Conover, F. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cooper, J. – Cotton, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Coulter, E. M. – Crane, Verner (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Craven, A. C. – Cresap, B. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Crittenden, C. C. – Daniels, J. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Davenport, G. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Davidson, Donald (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Davidson, John – Davidson, Philip (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Davis, Charles – Dawson, Ed (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Denbo, Bruce – Denson, N. D. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Deschamps, M. – Dewitt, Mrs. John (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Dickerson, O. M. – Dorris, J. T. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Doster, James F. – Dunning, William A. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - D. Van Nostrand (Brown, Harold – Gum, W. L. ) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - D. Van Nostrand (Heany, A. G. – Vietor, O. A.) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - D. Van Nostrand (Crane, E. M. ) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dyer, J. P. – Dykes, R. O. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Eades, William – Evans, Edward H. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fain, Tyree – Flanders, Ralph (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fleming, Walter L. – Fletcher, John G. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ford, Guy Stanton – Fulton, R. E. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gachel, D. – Going, Allen (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Govan, Tom – Green, Fletcher (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Greene, J. N. – Hall, Martin (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hamilton, Mrs. Henry C. – Harper, R. M. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Harrell, C. J. – Hill, Walter (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hingers, Edward J. – Holt, W. S. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Holton, Holland – Howard, G. H. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Howell, Isabel (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Howell, Isabel (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Howell, Morton B. – Huff, A. L. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Ingram, I. S. – Jones, Millard Van (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Jordan, Holman – Jordan, Weymouth T. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Karl, Barry – Kiger, Joe (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Kilby, T. – Kuhlman, A. F. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Landrith, Harold F. – Latimer, John F. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Lazenby, C. – Little, Brown and Company (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lloyd, Arthur Young – Locket, Mary (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lord, Clifford – Lynch, William O. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Lytle, Andrew N. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - McCann, Thomas – McIntosh, J. W. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - McLaughlin, A. – MacPherson, Joseph (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Manning, John – Martin, Thomas (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Meacham, Boyd – Mississippi Valley Historical Association (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Moe, Henry Allen – Moffitt, James W. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Mooney, Chase (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Moore, A. B. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Moore, A. B. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Moore, A. B. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Moore, A. B. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Moore, Charles – Morris, Richard B. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Morton, Richard L. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Nettels, Curtis – Nichols, Roy F. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Nixon, Herman C. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Odum, Howard – Ownbey, Richard L. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Palmer, Gordon D. – Peel, Roy V. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Pentecost, Percy – Pipkin, C. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Pomfret, John E. – Ramsdell, Charles (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Ramsey, John – Rich, Celia (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Richardson, Patrick – Roberts, Francis (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Robinson, Janie Grace – Schlesinger, A. M. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Schmidt, L. B. – Silver, Jim (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Simms, Henry – Simpson, Robert (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Skipper, O. C. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Smith, C. E. – Snyder, Louis (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Social Science Research Council (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - South, Percy – Staples, T. S. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Stephenson, W. H. - Sterkx, Gene (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Stevens, George – Stone, Geoffrey (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Strode, Hudson – Summersell, Charles (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Swint, Henry Lee (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Swint, Henry Lee (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Sydnor, Charles – Tansill, Charles (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Tate, Allen (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Tate, Allen – Tate, Caroline G. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - ten Hoor, Marten – Thach, Harry (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Thistlewaite, Frank – Thrasher, James D. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Tidwell, R. E. – Vance, Rupert B. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Vandiver, Frank – Venable, Austin (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Vipond, Herbert E. – Volwiler, A. T. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Wade, John Donald (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Walker, “Doc” – Walser, Zeb V. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Walters, Bennett (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Walters, Bennett (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Watson, Elliott (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Weaver, Blanche Henry (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Weaver, Blanche Henry (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Weaver, Blanche Henry (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Weaver, Blanche Henry (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Weaver, Herbert (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Weber, Bernard – Wiley, Bill (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Wilkerson, M. M. – Williams, Charlotte (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Williams, Clanton (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Williams, Clanton (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Williams, C. E. – Wuorinen, John (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Yale Review – Yeatman, Mary W. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Young, Francis – Younger, Edward (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Writings
  - Book Manuscripts
    - Index (29 pages) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Plain Folk of the Old South, “Southern Folkways,” delivered as lectures at Louisiana State University. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Plain Folk of the Old South, “To the Promised Land,” chapters delivered as lectures at LSU. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Plain Folk of the Old South, “Some Characteristics and Influences,” chapters delivered as lectures at LSU (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Plain Folk of the Old South, “Statistical Analysis of Land and Slave Holdings in Sample Counties.” (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Plain Folk of the Old South, “Some Observations of the Population of the South, 1840 – 1860,” Chapter III “By the Sweat of Their Brows,” Chapter IV “The Role of the Plain Folk.” (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy (1959 Revision) includes memorial Foreword by William C. Binkley (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy (1959 Revision)—Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy (1959 Revision)---Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy (1959 Revision)---Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy—published copy. Revised and corrected by Owsley for the 2nd edition. Part 1. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - King Cotton Diplomacy—published copy. Revised and corrected by Owsley for the 2nd edition. Part 2. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Selected Essays of Frank Lawrence Owsley— Introductory material, chronology, Foreword by Andrew Lytle. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Selected Essays, “The Pattern of Migration and Settlement on the Southern Frontier” (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Selected Essays, “The Plain Folk and their Role in Southern History” (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Selected Essays, “The Fundamental Cause of the Civil War: Egocentric Sectionalism” (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Selected Essays, “Local Defence and the Overthrow of the Confederacy: A Study in State Rights” (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Selected Essays, “Defeatism in the Confederacy” (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Selected Essays, “Why Europe Did Not Intervene” (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Selected Essays, “America and the Freedom of the Seas, 1861 – 1865” (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Selected Essays, “The Pillars of Agrarianism” (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Selected Essays, “Democracy Unlimited” (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Selected Essays, “The Making of Andrew Jackson” (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Selected Essays, “Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus Lamar” (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Selected Essays, “A Rebel War Clerk and His Diary” (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Selected Essays, “A Southerner’s View of Abraham Lincoln (1958) (original draft of speech) (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Selected Essays, “A Southerner’s View of Abraham Lincoln” (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Selected Essays, “The Soldier Who Walked with God” (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Unpublished Book Manuscripts
    - Mexico, Chapter I (revised) (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Mexico, “The Confederacy and Mexico: John T. Pickett, Swashbuckler” (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Mexico, Chapter III, “ The Troubled Waters of Mexico” (typed) (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Mexico, Chapter III, “ The Troubled Waters of Mexico” (early draft) (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Mexico, “Juan A. Quinterro’s Mission to the Border States” (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Articles, Essays, and Speeches
    - “The Confederacy and King Cotton”, (1929) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - “The Economic Basis of Society in the Late Ante-Bellum South” (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - “The Education of a Southern Frontier Girl, Mary Jane Walker” (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - “The Education of a Southern Frontier Girl” (revision), (1953-1954) (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - “John Williams Walker”, (1956) (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - “ Origin of the American Civil War”, (1940) (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - “World is Seen as Drifting into Another War” (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - “The Writing of Local History”, (1954) (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Unpublished Articles, Essays, and Speeches
    - “The Art of Boot Licking” (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - “The Chief Stakes of the South in World Affairs Today” (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - “The Confederacy and King Cotton: A Study in Economic Coercion” (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - “Ed Taylor, Tenant Farmer” (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - “The Foundations of History” (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Fulbright Lecture, St. John’s College, Cambridge, England 1956 (Rough draft) (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - “General Henry Delamar Clayton” (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - “How Communism Wins the Support of the Masses” (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - “The Making of George Washington” (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - “My Impressions of England” (xerox of Ms) (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - “Presentation of Essays in Honor of William E. Dodd” (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - “Problems that Determined the Radical Policy of Reconstruction” (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - “Whither the White Councils? Letter to the Editor of the Tuscaloosa News” (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - “Wills, etc.” (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Book Reviews
    - The Blue and the Gray (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Confederate Georgia by T. Conn Bryan (Athens: The University of Georgia Press, 1953) (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - The Disruption of American Democracy. By Roy Franklin Nichols. (New York: The Macmillan Co., 1948). (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - French Opinion on the United States and Mexico, 1860 – 1867. By Lynn M. Case (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - The Growth of Southern Nationalism 1848 –1861. By Avery O. Craven. Vol. VI, A History of the South. (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1953). (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Jefferson in Power: The Death Struggleof the Federalists. By Claude G. Bowers, 1936 (Houghton Mifflin Co.) (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - The Memoirs of Lieutenant Henry Timberlake, 1756 – 1765. Edited by Samuel Cole Williams (Johnson City, Tennessee: the Watauga Press) (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - The Secession Movement in Virginia, 1847 – 1861. By Henry T. Shanks (Garrett and Massie) (Box 8, Folder 35)
- Personal and Biographical Materials
  - Photocopy of Frank Owsley’s memoir (44 pages) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Owsley’s offer to H. T. Vance Company to purchase Real Estate, (1937) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Remembrances of Frank L. Owsley (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Warranty deed, Hotel reservation, Lotus Club (NYC) privileges, Who’s Who in America (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - World War I—discharge from draft, Transportation request, Order of induction into military service of the U.S., Local board for the county of Elmore, State of Alabama, Honorable discharge (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - European Trip—Menus, receipts, tourbook, postcard (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Letters of Recommendation/Introduction (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Photograph (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Condolences to Harriet C. Owsley (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Condolences to Harriet C. Owsley (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Agrarians and Fugitives
  - Collecting Papers of Agrarians/Fugitives—Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Fugitive Reunion, 1956 –Programs (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Articles—Who Owns America? (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Articles—The South (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Publication Materials
  - Reviews of State Rights in the Confederacy (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Reviews of State Rights in the Confederacy (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Reviews of King Cotton Diplomacy (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - King Cotton Diplomacy— Copyright (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Reviews of A Short History of the American People (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - A Short History of the American People, Textbook Adoption Lists, 1948 – 1955 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Reviews of Plain Folk of the Old South (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Plain Folk of the Old South— Contract (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - List of Articles by Frank Lawrence Owsley (Box 9, Folder 26)
- Professional Activities
  - Organizations
    - Alabama Historical Association—Programs (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - American Historical Association (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Mississippi Valley Historical Association—Programs (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Southern Historical Association—Records, minutes, and list of members (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Southern Historical Association—Programs, 1937, 1938, 1940, 1948, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Southern Illinois Historical Society—Programs (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Tennessee Historical Commission (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Events
    - Fleming Lectures, Louisiana State University, 1948 – Newspaper articles (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Fleming Lectures, Louisiana State University—Programs – 4 lectures given by Owsley April 12, 13, and 14, 1948 “Southern Society—A Reinterpretation” “To the Promised Land: Migration and Settlement of the Plain Folk” “Southern Folkways” and “The Role of the Plain Folk” (Box 9, Folder 35)